Guide to the Michael Fox Papers
Special Collections, University of Washington Libraries
Michael Fox papers
1961-1997
1971-1974
University of Washington Libraries Special Collections Box 352900 Seattle, WA 98195-2900
5926
5926-001
Fox, Michael J.$q(Michael James),$d1944-
2.28 cubic feet 2 box
Records relating to Michael Fox's role as a United Farmworkers of Washington lawyer
Judge Michael James Fox was born in New London, Connecticut in 1944. During the 1960s, he became politically active in the Civil Rights Movement. While attending law school in Georgia, Fox was part of the Legal Aid Society—an organization that provided legal services to people from low-income backgrounds. After law school, his experience with the Legal Aid Society greatly influenced his decision to continue to help underrepresented people. Having also acquired Spanish speaking skills, Fox became interested in working with the large population of Spansih-speaking Latino/a farmworkers. In 1965, the US Congress created the Office of Economic Opportunity which funded the Legal Services Program, a private non-profit corporation providing legal services to people living in poverty. In that same year, a strike of Filipino American grape pickers in Delano, California gained the cooperation of Cesar Chavez and others, who began organizing migrant agricultural workers in California. Using the same organizing model, workers in Washington State organized an independent branch of the United Farm Workers of Washington State in 1967. In 1969, Fox moved to Washington through the Reginald Heber Smith Fellowship, a program that places lawyers in areas to help those who do not have access to legal aid, and discovered that the state had the fourth largest migrant farmworker population in the country. In the following year, the wildcat hop strikes began in the Yakima Valley. Fox connected with the organizers of the hop strikes, Tomás Villanueva and Lupe Gamboa, and offered to provide legal representation to the emerging farmworkers union. As the UFW lawyer, Fox in Garza v. Patnode (1971) argued successfully that farmworkers had the right to organize. In that same year, Fox and Lupe Gamboa were arrested and convicted for trespassing onto the Roger’s Walla Walla labor camp. Their convictions were eventually overturned and the decision confirmed that tenants in labor camps had the right to meet with union representatives and attorneys. Both cases were instrumental to the early efforts of the union (see State v. Fox, 1973 ). Fox continued to provide legal representation to the UFW until 1988. In that year Fox became a King County Superior Court Judge. On the bench, Fox called attention to the treatment of minorities in the legal system, particularly related to drug sentencing. Fox retired in 2011 after a distinguished judicial career.
Organized into 2 accessions.
Accession No. 5926-001, Michael Fox papers, 1971-1974, 1994
Accession No. 5926-002, Michael J. Fox papers, 1961-1997
This collection traces a series of legal cases arising out of the June 19, 1971 arrest for trespassing of Seattle-King County Legal Services attorney Michael Fox and union organizer Guadalupe Gamboa of the UFW Co-op in Toppenish. Fox and Gamboa visited the Rogers Walla Walla Inc. migrant labor camp following Gamboa’s contact with workers there who had grievances regarding their working and living conditions. When they attempted to meet with workers, Rogers employees refused them entry without their naming the individuals they were meeting with and the purpose of their meeting. Fox and Gamboa refused to provide names, reasoning that employees named would be in potential danger of losing their jobs or worse. Rogers representatives called the sheriff who arrested Fox and Gamboa for trespassing and fined them $25 each. Fox and Gamboa appealed their conviction to the Superior Court of the County of Walla Walla, which affirmed the conviction in December 1971. Fox and Gamboa then appealed to the Washington State Supreme Court, which reversed the finding of the Superior Court in May 1973. This established an important precedent for future organizers and attorneys in the state. The State of Washington sought a hearing in the United State Supreme Court, which refused to hear the case. In Fox v. Klundt [Walla Walla County Sheriff] et al, Fox brought a civil suit against representatives of Rogers Walla Walla for damages and received a settlement of $6,000. Records include legal materials and newspaper articles relating to the court cases. Other records relate to the State of Washington State v. Michael Fox, 1973.
No restrictions on access.
Michael J. Fox, 2016.
Labor unions$zWashington (State); Labor$zWashington (State); Labor movement$zWashington (State); Labor union members$zWashington (State); Records (Documents); Personal correspondence; Legal instruments; Labor Archives of Washington (University of Washington), $e host institution; Fox, Michael J.$q(Michael James),$d1944- $vArchives; Fox, Michael J.$q(Michael James),$d1944- $vTrials, litigation, etc.; Washington (State)$vTrials, litigation, etc.; Gamboa, Guadalupe; Gamboa, Guadalupe$vTrials, litigation, etc.; Labor Archives of Washington (University of Washington); United Farm Workers Organizing Committee; Lawyers$zWashington (State)$vArchives; Labor disputes$zWashington (State); Agricultural laborers$zWashington (State); Agricultural laborers$xLabor unions$xOrganizing$zWashington (State); Agricultural laborers$xLabor unions$zWashington (State); Migrant agricultural laborers$zWashington (State); Migrant agricultural laborers$xLabor unions$xOrganizing$zWashington (State); Migrant agricultural laborers$xLabor unions$zWashington (State); Personal Papers/Corporate Records; Labor History; Labor Unions; Civil Rights; Latinos and Latinas; Agriculture
- Michael Fox papers, 1971-1974, 1994; 5926-001; 1.14 cubic feet 1 box
  This collection traces a series of legal cases arising out of the June 19, 1971 arrest for trespassing of Seattle-King County Legal Services attorney Michael Fox and union organizer Guadalupe Gamboa of the UFW Co-op in Toppenish. Fox and Gamboa visited the Rogers Walla Walla Inc. migrant labor camp following Gamboa's contact with workers there who had grievances regarding their working and living conditions. When they attempted to meet with workers, Rogers employees refused them entry without their naming the individuals they were meeting with and the purpose of their meeting. Fox and Gamboa refused to provide names, reasoning that employees named would be in potential danger of losing their jobs or worse. Rogers representatives called the sheriff who arrested Fox and Gamboa for trespassing and fined them $25 each. Fox and Gamboa appealed their conviction to the Superior Court of the County of Walla Walla, which affirmed the conviction in December 1971. Fox and Gamboa then appealed to the Washington State Supreme Court, which reversed the finding of the Superior Court in May 1973. This established an important precedent for future organizers and attorneys in the state. The State of Washington sought a hearing in the United State Supreme Court, which refused to hear the case. In Fox v. Klundt [Walla Walla County Sheriff] et al, Fox brought a civil suit against representatives of Rogers Walla Walla for damages and received a settlement of $6,000. Records include legal materials and newspapers articles relating to the court cases. Other records relate to the State of Washington v. Michael Fox, 1973.
  No restrictions on access.
  Michael J. Fox, 2016
  - COURT CASES, 1971-1974,1994; SERIES I (Box-folder 1/1-1/15)
    - Events of June 1971 (Box-folder 1/1)
    - Walla Walla County Court, 1971-1972 (Box-folder 1/2)
    - Washington State Superior Court, Walla Walla County, 1971-1972 (Box-folder 1/3)
    - Washington State Superior Court, Walla Walla County, 1972 (Box-folder 1/4)
    - Preparation for State of Washington v. Fox, 1972 (Box-folder 1/5)
    - Washington State Supreme Court, State of Washington v. Fox Appeal--Part 1 of 6, 1972 (Box-folder 1/6)
    - Washington State Supreme Court, State of Washington v. Fox Appeal--Part 2 of 6, 1972 (Box-folder 1/7)
    - Washington State Supreme Court, State of Washington v. Fox Appeal--Part 3 of 6, 1972 (Box-folder 1/8)
    - Washington State Supreme Court, State of Washington v. Fox Appeal--Part 4 of 6, 1971-1972 (Box-folder 1/9)
    - Washington State Supreme Court, State of Washington v. Fox Appeal--Part 5 of 6, 1972 (Box-folder 1/10)
    - Washington State Supreme Court, State of Washington v. Fox Appeal--Part 6 of 6, 1972-1973 (Box-folder 1/11)
    - U.S. District Court, Fox v. Klundt--Part 1 of 2, 1971-1972 (Box-folder 1/12)
    - U.S. District Court, Fox v. Klundt--Part 2 of 2, 1971-1974 (Box-folder 1/13)
    - U.S. Supreme Court--State of Washington v. Fox, 1973 (Box-folder 1/14)
    - Additional Materials Related to Court Cases, 1974-1994 (Box-folder 1/15)
- Michael J. Fox papers, 1961-1997; 1970s; 5926-002; 1.14 cubic feet 1 carton
  This collection is primarily comprised of documents relating to the State of Washington v. Fox court case and appeals process, which spanned from 1971-1974. The case began on June 19th, 1971 when Michael Fox and Guadalupe Gamboa were arrested for trespassing in a migrant workers camp run by the Rogers Walla Walla Company. A transcript from the case relating to the incident is in Box 1, Folder 5. After being found guilty in the District court (Box 1, Folders 10 and 14), Fox and Gamboa took the case through the appeals process where it finally was heard by the Washington State Supreme Court, (Box 1, Folder 21-23). The Supreme Court ruled in favor of Fox and Gamboa and therefore set a legal precedent of the right of lawyers and union organizers to have access to migrant workers on private lands. The collection contains documentation and transcripts from all of the trials as well as the pre-trial correspondence between Fox and various organizations in his effort to secure amicus briefs (Box 1, Folder 13-15). Multiple articles relating to the case have also been placed into this collection (Box 1, Folders 4, 27 and 32). In addition, there are articles about Michael Fox’s career as a judge (Box 1, Folder 37, 38), as well as articles that Fox wrote or that he collected (Box 1, Folders 26, 30, 31, 34 and 35).
  Donated by Michael Fox in March 2016.